Political centism. The set of beliefs
known for its success back in 1930s
Europe, whose proponents were rewarded
for their political acumen after a few
years by getting to be the smugest
people in the concentration camp. Did
you know that Hitler has lied on average
about 10 times a day for the past 5
years? We know. We fact checked him. How
do we respond to that? Yes, that's very
nice. Please step into the chamber. Now,
fast forward 100 years and the political
center around the Western world is once
again dying. The old establishment
parties are decaying, breaking apart and
becoming irrelevant in most of the
developed democratic world. The most
glaring example here is the United
States where the centrist democrats led
by energetic, charismatic, dying
septtogenarians were beaten even by the
mega movement. And so Democrats in-house
necromancers have been working around
the clock to try and reanimate the
recent presidential candidate for an
interview to help regain lost support.
Unfortunately, Joe Biden's earthly
remains failed to make any waves due to
his advanced state of decay. regain
control of what we invented the control
of the the future. So centrists look at
the current political landscape. They
look at people's overwhelming
dissatisfaction and disillusionment with
the status quo and ask themselves what
could be the problem. So people are like
look the problem is that we don't feel
like the system is working for us
anymore. Uh we get poorer while the rich
get richer. It feels like the economy
has become a scheme to uh funnel our
money to the top and keep it there.
Prices are up. Housing is unaffordable.
Everything around us is turning to [__]
due to corporate profitering. Google is
unusable now. Uh Facebook and Twitter
are 24/7 Nazi rallies. AI is flooding
everything. Uh public services are being
cut back and or privatized. Our income
doesn't keep up with inflation. And we
generally feel like our votes don't
matter anymore because you guys are
doing nothing to fix systemic issues.
That's the problem. And centrists are
like, "Yeah, okay. That's great.
Whatever. Anyway, what could be the
problem?" But what's that? Here comes a
new challenger who has listened to all
your problems and decided that the
solution to systemic issues with the
global economy is ethnic nationalism. If
you hate brown people, gays, and or Jews
hard enough, the systemic problems will
be gone or something. I don't know. The
far right world is one where all
economic issues, the systemic problems,
the wealth inequality pretty much stays
the exact same, but now pride is banned.
Also, democracy is basically gone. So,
you know, mission accomplished. Like in
Hungary, where after 15 years of based
Victor Orban and his Christian
nationalist government, Hungary has the
worst healthcare in Europe, one of the
worst education systems. The rail
network is falling apart. Social
mobility is nearly zero with Hungarians
paying the highest taxes in Europe.
Meanwhile, Orban lives in a castle. So
do his cronies and his various other
supplicants drive around the country in
Ferraris, Lamborghinis, and Bentleys,
and are also seen chilling on
multi-million dollar superyachts off the
Italian coast. Orban also had a football
stadium built in his home village
because [__] it, why not? Elsewhere,
centrist politicians look upon the
surging farright and ask, "Oh, how could
this happen? How could the farright
become so popular after we let them
openly propagandize and undermine our
democracy for a decade, mainly through
social media, which we refused to
regulate? Who would have known that they
are a threat to democracy after they
spent the last 10 years screaming about
rigged elections and inciting mobs to
forcefully overturn elections, the
result of which they didn't like? We are
quite simply flabbergasted by these
developments. Who would have thought
that letting malicious fake news run
rampant across the media is a bad idea?
In the so-called free marketplace of
ideas, the truth does not stand a chance
against billionaire funded propaganda.
Thankfully, Ground News is here to help
balance the scales in your favor. Ground
News gathers well news from all over the
world, enabling you to see how different
sources report on the same story, giving
you a more complete balanced overview of
events. Let's take an example. The story
about Putin not attending peace talks in
Turkey. At the time of recording, this
story has been covered by 386 articles
with a fairly even distribution of 58
left-leaning, 52 right-leaning, and 74
centrist sources. Here we can see that
most sources are of high effectuality.
And below you'll find a breakdown of
their ownership structure. Ground news
also comes with a bias comparison
feature summarizing the aspects each
political side chooses to focus on. In
this case, left-leaning sources focus on
Putin being bad faith and manipulative
by not attending peace talks, while the
right focuses on Putin chickening out
and blowing his big chance with Trump.
Ground News is your ultimate guide in
today's news ecosystem, enabling you to
stay on top of the news cycle. Go to
ground.news/adam or scan this QR code to
receive 40% off their vantage plan with
unlimited access to every feature. Or
you can try their pro plan for just $1 a
month. Thank you for checking out Ground
News.
[Music]
The only political force willing to
stand up to the farright is various
leftist political movements, many of
which have seen a considerable boost in
support. Recently, Germany's Dinka
rebounded during the last election and
gained 25 additional seats in the
Bundesag. This is after Saravagenact
split the party in half and went on to
found her brand new Nazi Bolevik party,
the pro-Russian leftist party, which
also just happens to oppose non-white
immigration. And it didn't make it into
the Bundustag. Close enough. The left's
performance has been even more
impressive in France, where the new
popular front coalition had gained 57
additional seats, thus becoming the
largest force in French parliament. So,
we have our political force opposing the
far right, right? Not so fast, yelled
the centrist. Leftists are also
radicals, and the radicalism is bad.
Therefore, the far right and the far
left are just as bad. One wants more
public housing and higher taxes on the
wealthy, while the other wants to put
LGBT people in concentration camps and
purge the country of non-whites. They
are literally the same. But centrist
politicians are in a bind here. They
need to go somewhere because their
current position is untenable. If they
don't go either left or right, the only
way for them is down. So some of them
figured their best shot is to start
moving towards the far right. But hey,
they can be fair and reasonable about
it. The far right wants to do a second
holocaust. Well, the centrist can surely
arrive at a reasonable compromise. How
about a half holocaust? which is
basically what happened in 1940s Hungary
by the way where Jews in the countryside
were all killed while Jews in the
capital were mostly spared initially.
Nowadays the UK's Kier Starmer and his
Labor party are perhaps the best example
of centrist striford movement. Starmer
has managed for some reason to steer a
formerly progressive and left-leaning
party towards policies championed by the
likes of Niguel Farage and his far-right
reform UK. Out of nowhere, Starmer came
out against trans people and various
other progressive causes. Then once in
power, he went on to do right-wing
austerity, public sector cuts, business
deregulation, in addition to announcing
large-scale deportations. Fast forward
to now, and this masterful political
gambit has collapsed the Labor Party and
boosted Reform UK to first place in
national polls. So, you know, oops. This
strategy of let's try to deflate the
farright by copying them would be
absolutely brilliant if it worked.
However, reality seems to be in denial
about stormers and similar centrists
ideas. Turns out if you become a bad
copy of the farright, you send a message
to the public that these ideas are now
mainstream and acceptable. Not only
that, but you prompt people to ask the
question, if we are voting for farright
stuff anyway, why not just vote for the
real thing? And British people do.
Mockron seems to share much of Starmer's
sentiment. In the aftermath of his
masterful snap- election gambit that saw
his party crater, an alliance of leftist
parties received the largest share of
votes. Traditionally, the new French
prime minister is to be nominated from
the ranks of the largest party, which
Macron decided to ignore. Because
according to him, leftists are just as
bad as the far right. One wants to purge
fronts of non-whites and degenerates,
while the other wants more public
housing and gay rights, literally the
same. But what if you are a centrist
politician who actually sees the writing
on the wall, who realizes that the
center is untenable and that moving
right means empowering the far right?
So, how about we move left instead? No.
Wait, who's that? Oh, right. It's the
billion-dollar donor class that finances
the centrist political machine made up
of people the left wants to tax. For
them, the question of should centrists
go left or right is basically, do I want
my taxes higher or lower? Oh well, far
right it is. Then some of you might die.
Non-whites, LGBT people, political
opponents, but that's a sacrifice the
top 1% is willing to make for tax cuts.
But suppose that you are the leader of a
progressive political party or a
centrist party even that is both able
and willing to move left. What can you
do to address the problems we're having?
The funneling of money to the top, the
decay of public services. How do you
regain people's trust? How do you regain
the electorate's trust? Well, first off,
we need to understand what happened. The
fallen standard of living tells a story.
The great post-war social contract was
shattered in our home across the ocean
in the Western world. Now, the welfare
state is nowhere to be found. And in the
1980s, the top marginal tax rate was the
first to perish. Soon, the finance
sector, billionaires, all claimed parts
of the economy. Their greed from their
newfound wealth triggered the 2008
economic crash. A crisis from which no
ordinary person arose. A crisis leading
to abandonment by the people's
trust. Long story short, the system no
longer abides by the postworld war II
unspoken social contract. And that
social contract is this. If you work a
full-time job, you should not have to
struggle. You should not have money
problems or lack in any basic needs. And
you should be able to afford a
reasonable amount of comfort and luxury
besides that. Basically, if you work
full-time, you should be able to afford
a middle class lifestyle. Period. If we
have billionaires taking joy rides into
space or uppart babies running the US
government, why can't we also have cheap
housing or cheap utilities? Why can't we
provide everyone with a base amount of
food so that no one has to worry about
feeding themselves or their family in
the developed world? This is the
billion-dollar question. So, here are
some step one type measures a government
can take to start regaining people's
trust and stem the oncoming tide of the
far right. Make public utilities public
here in Czecha. I once saw a job advert
for CHZ. That's the biggest utility
company in the country for electricity
and gas. They were looking for a
full-time stock market day trader. But
just why does a utility company need a
stock market day trader? What part of
supplying the population with
electricity and gas involves stock
market day trading? None of the Czech
utility sector and many many others in
many other countries had been thoroughly
financialized. They are part of the
finance sector now. And this might seem
like a good idea on paper. You know, we
have this big company with all these
assets. So why not use its wealth to
make even more money on the stock
market? But the stock market doesn't
always go up, does it? Sometimes it goes
the opposite direction. especially if a
bunch of finance bros start gambling
with it. And that's when the government
needs to do expensive bailouts. If you
put a company on the stock market, it
will become far more vulnerable to
market cycles. So why put them on the
stock market? This is what Yonis Vufakis
calls the financialization of
everything. Public utilities should be
public but not on the stock market. They
should be nonprofit. The goal is to
provide people with services, not to
make money. But the financialization of
state services is still the lesser evil.
Worst is when a democratic state lets go
of a sector seemingly for no reason.
This is called privatization. The only
real purpose of which is to serve up
more of the economy to the oligarchs.
Why do you think the US government is
privatizing its space sector, cutting
the budget of NASA and increasingly
relying on SpaceX? And the answer is so
that Elon Musk and Jeff Bezos can own
the sector. Simple as that. Meanwhile,
down here on Earth, have you ever
wondered why there aren't any state-run
housing construction companies? It's all
private developers now. And how are
these developers fairing? Well, if we
choose to ignore the ongoing
catastrophic housing crisis across the
Western world for the past decade, then
not too bad, I guess. Yes, the housing
sector has also been thoroughly
privatized and financialized. The
housing sector should be nonprofit and
publicly owned as far as it can provide
everyone with housing should they need
it. If someone wants to operate a
private real estate market beyond that,
that's all right. The idea is that no
one has to rely on the private market
because there is always a strong
highquality public option. Also, let's
get a food UBI going. That's universal
basic income. Let's give people a set
amount of meal vouchers each month,
which they can use at grocery stores,
and restaurants. Wow, would you look at
that? We have restored the postw World
War II social contract. People now have
affordable housing, utilities, and
groceries, putting them in a vastly
improved financial situation and taking
a ton of pressure and worries off their
backs. What's that? The far right
stopped rising because their message of
everything is going to [__] and only
white nationalism can help us no longer
resonates because things are no longer
going to [__] Wow, imagine my shock.
Deprivatizing and defanializing our
basic services means taking power away
from the oligarchs and giving it to our
democratically run states. And I would
do the same thing with healthcare,
education, and also internet service
providers. I believe this to be the
first step to regain people's trust in
the system and stop the rise of the far
right. Let's take back control, one
could say. But this time for real.
[Music]